<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:distill="https://distill.pub/journal/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Aurèle Toussaint</title>
    <link>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>My Blog
</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Estonian Research Award</title>
      <link>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-02-09-estonianaward</link>
      <description>


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776//posts/2024-02-09-estonianaward/smartcrop.jpeg" alt="Riigi teaduspreemiate pidulik üleandmine 2023. aastal. Autor/allikas: Birgit Püve" width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;
(#fig:unnamed-chunk-1)Riigi teaduspreemiate pidulik üleandmine 2023.
aastal. Autor/allikas: Birgit Püve
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very proud and happy to belong to the team led by Carlos P.
Carmona, Riin Tamme and Meelis Pärtel and being awarded by Estonia for
our recent research findings !! Nothing would have been possible without
the &lt;a href="https://etag.ee/en/" target="_blank"&gt;Estonian Research
Council (ETAG)&lt;/a&gt; who support my research during 7 years. I also do not
forget that Guillermo Bueno was fully part of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We received this award for our research on the functional diversity
of plants and vertebrates at global scale. This project was develop
around several scientific papers published in top-level journals. Among
the high diversity of papers published, I recommend to read the papers
published in
&lt;a href="https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/sciadv.abf2675" target="_blank"&gt;Sciences
Advances&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-25293-0" target="_blank"&gt;Nature
Communications&lt;/a&gt;. In those papers we investigated the diversity of
functional traits for each group of vertebrates and plants at global and
regional scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several associate papers have been published and might interested
people to dig more deeply on the world of functional diversity and
trait-based approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more about Estonian Research Award at &lt;a
href="https://novaator.err.ee/1609246851/teaduse-elutoopreemiad-palvisid-jakob-kubarsepp-ja-raivo-uibo"
class="uri"&gt;https://novaator.err.ee/1609246851/teaduse-elutoopreemiad-palvisid-jakob-kubarsepp-ja-raivo-uibo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="r distill-force-highlighting-css"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <distill:md5>f44faf1fea6ca29310a7315f97164e7d</distill:md5>
      <category>news</category>
      <guid>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-02-09-estonianaward</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-02-09-estonianaward/smartcrop.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper accepted in Ecology Letters</title>
      <link>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters</link>
      <description>


&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full paper &lt;a href="" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Citation:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Toussaint A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Pärtel M., Carmona
C.P., 2024 Contrasting impacts of non-native and threatened species on
morphological, life-history, and phylogenetic diversity in bird
assemblages, &lt;em&gt;Ecology Letters&lt;/em&gt;, Accepted&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="context"&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The composition of assemblages worldwide has been strongly modified
by human activities throughout the introduction of non-native and the
extirpation of threatened species. Those changes not only affected the
number of species but also the functional and phylogenetic structure of
the communities, which might affect the ecosystem functioning. However,
it is still unclear whether non-native species could compensate for the
potential loss of threatened species and hence maintain ecosystem
functioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="aims"&gt;Aims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we tested whether bird non-natives species are functionally
and/or phylogenetically similar (i.e., compensation hypothesis) or
distinct (i.e., shift hypothesis) from threatened species on bird
assemblages in 281 regions worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="main-findings"&gt;Main findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings indicate that shifts in species composition could
trigger a global decline in avian biodiversity due to the high number of
threatened species. Furthermore, these losses are not random; they
disproportionally involve species that are functionally and
phylogenetically unique at the regional scale. Our results show that
non-native species are not able to offset these changes because they are
morphologically and phylogenetically close to native fauna.
Consequently, our results emphasize the need for both controlling
non-native species and preserving phylogenetically unique native
species, which are the primary drivers of changes in the functional and
phylogenetic structure of bird communities. These findings contribute to
our understanding of the complex dynamics shaping global biodiversity
and inform conservation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776//posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters/Figure_1_R2.png" alt="Changes in taxonomic, morphological, life-history, and phylogenetic richness in 281 regions across the world." width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;
(#fig:unnamed-chunk-1)Changes in taxonomic, morphological, life-history,
and phylogenetic richness in 281 regions across the world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="methodological-novelty"&gt;Methodological novelty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide a more nuanced understanding of functional diversity, we
distinguished morphological from life-history traits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Functional diversity is a multi-faceted concept that encompasses a
range of traits affecting species’ roles in ecosystems. Traditionally,
studies have aggregated traits into a single measure of functional
diversity. We adopted a different approach by dissecting functional
diversity into two morphological diversity and life-history
diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We collected 11 morphological traits from the AVONET database for
9,981 species
(&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/ele.13898" target="_blank"&gt;Tobias
et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;) relative to beak length (Culmen and Nares), width, and
depth, tarsus length, wing length, Kipps distance, hand-wing index, tail
length, secondary, and body mass (Table S1). These traits influence
various ecological functions like seed dispersal, predation, and
resource utilization
(&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0169534706000334" target="_blank"&gt;McGill
et al. 2006&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eight life-history traits were retrieved from the AMNIOTE database
for 8,940 species
(&lt;a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1890/15-0846R.1" target="_blank"&gt;Myhrvold
et al. 2015&lt;/a&gt;): clutch size, number of clutches per year, incubation
time, longevity, fledging age, egg mass and distance from the tip of the
beak to the opening of the cloaca and body mass (Table S1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes in species composition led to deeper variations in
morphological dissimilarity and phylogenetic dissimilarity (r = 0.45, P
&amp;lt; 0.001, Fig. 2A) than in life-history dissimilarity, which showed
only a weak correlation with other diversity facets (r &amp;lt; 0.20, P &amp;lt;
0.01, Fig. 2B, C). For instance, in Asia, the decrease in morphological
dissimilarity was lower-than-expected in 37% of regions while the
life-history dissimilarity was not significant. In contrast, in Western
Europe, 36% of the regions experienced a decrease lower-than-expected in
morphological dissimilarity but not in life-history dissimilarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776//posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters/Figure_4_R1.png" alt="Correlation between standardized effect sizes between morphological, life-history, and phylogenetic dissimilarity." width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;
(#fig:unnamed-chunk-2)Correlation between standardized effect sizes
between morphological, life-history, and phylogenetic dissimilarity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The observed discrepancies between morphological and life-history
traits can be attributed to the distribution of species within the
morphological and life-history spaces (Fig. 3). Indeed, non-native
species were more distant from native fauna in terms of life-history
traits than morphological traits, with these differences being
especially pronounced along the PC2 axis. This accounted for the
higher-than-expected losses observed in life-history richness but also
for the higher-than-expected decrease in dissimilarity for morphological
traits. Conversely, for threatened species, we did not observe
significant differences between the two sets of traits in the functional
spaces and PC2 and even slightly higher for PC1 in morphological traits,
explaining higher congruence in patterns for threatened species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776//posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters/Figure_5_R1.png" alt="Functional uniqueness of non-native and threatened species between morphological and life-history traits." width="100%" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;
(#fig:unnamed-chunk-3)Functional uniqueness of non-native and threatened
species between morphological and life-history traits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre class="r distill-force-highlighting-css"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <distill:md5>2a3bdfe0f2c3e940733da5c0acd28870</distill:md5>
      <category>articles</category>
      <guid>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-paper-accepted-in-ecology-letters/Figure_1_R2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="3000" height="3000"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New position in CNRS</title>
      <link>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-position-in-cnrs</link>
      <description>Researcher position in Toulouse</description>
      <category>position</category>
      <guid>https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-position-in-cnrs</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://beta.rstudioconnect.com/content/3776/posts/2024-01-17-new-position-in-cnrs/logoCNRSEDB.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1058" height="595"/>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
